Guide to the Helen M. Stummer Photograph Collection 1976-1984 PR 235
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Helen M. Stummer Photograph Collection
1976-1984
PR 235
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.8 Linear feet (22 photographs, documentary material)
Photographs of residents of East 6th Street, New York City.
Provenance
In 2003 ten photographs were purchased from the photographer, who then donated twelve more photographs.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Helen M. Stummer was born in 1936. She holds a bachelor's degree in fine arts from Kean College, and a masters degree in Visual Sociology from Vermont College. Before becoming a photographer, Stummer was a painter. She began taking photographs in 1975, enrolling in classes at the International Center for Photography in New York City, in order to better document subjects for her paintings.
Stummer considers herself a Visual Sociologist. She has focused her camera on photographing economically disadvantaged communities, both in urban and rural settings. In addition to the photographs taken on East 6th Street found in this collection, she has documented inhabitants of the city of Newark, New Jersey, as well as communities in rural Maine and in Guatemala.
Stummer's photographs have been widely published and exhibited. More information on Stummer can be found on her website, www.hmstummer.com.
Scope and Content Note
The Helen M. Stummer Photograph Collection spans the period from 1976 to 1984 and primarily contains photographs taken on East 6th Street in New York City. The collection also holds some of the photographer's archive relating to these photographs.
While Stummer was enrolled in photography classes at the International Center for Photography, she was encouraged to continue an earlier interest in photographing children. She arranged to go to the Children's Aid Society's Sloane Center on East 6th Street between Avenues B and C. At that time the street was considered part of the Lower East Side neighborhood, and was inhabited mainly by poor Puerto Rican and African American families. Stummer photographed children both inside the Center and outside on the streets. Over the course of several years, she befriended many East 6th Street residents, and photographed important events in their lives. She also conducted oral interviews with some of the people she met and photographed.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in two series.
Series I: Photographs
Series II: Archive Material
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society Lbrary
A catalog from an exhibition of Stummer's photographs of Newark, New Jersey, No Easy Walk: Voices of the inner city (Miami, FL: Frances Wolfson Art Gallery, Miami-Dade Community College, 1991), is held by the New-York Historical Society's Library.
Audiocassettes; Contact sheets; Documentary photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Gelatin silver prints; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Poor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; Slides (photographs).; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York
- Series I: Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Photographs includes twenty-two 11x14 black and white photographs taken on East 6th Street between 1977 and 1980. The photographs have been loosely arranged by subject. Seven photographs show a woman named Shirley and her four children over a period of two years. Other photographs show individual portraits of children, street scenes of children and adults playing and lounging, and a few images of adults and children. Each photograph has been titled, dated, and signed by the photographer on the verso of each photograph. Titles recorded below are transcribed from the verso.
  Photographs are arranged loosely by subject, and thereunder by date. Titles are the photographer's.
  - Shirley and family
    - Shirley and Cornell grooming their children, East 6th St. NYC, 1978 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Shirley, her four children - Sam, Charlie, Yvette, and Bernadette - in backyard with neighborhood - East 6th St. NYC, 1978 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Before Christening - Shirley in middle, Cornell on right with their children, 1978 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bernadette, Yvette, Charlie, and baby (Shirley's children), 1979 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Twins combing Shirley's hair - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shirley with baby in gutter water - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shirley's twin daughter Yvette in kitchen, 1979 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Children and Adults
    - Lenny holding Michelle, 1977 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nancy (pregnant belly). Her daughter Michelle imitating, East 6th St. NYC, 1978 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pedro holding his niece (bike in foreground) East 6th St. NYC, 1978 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Helen and Charlie, 1980 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Children
    - The Graduate, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2 girls with dolls, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Boy with glasses in lower east side lot, 1977 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alberto E 6th St. NYC, 1978 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Groups of Children
    - Neighborhood friends East 6th St. NYC, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Volleyball in front of Sloan Center street - East 6th St. NYC, 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Playing in street - hydrant water - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Summer camp marching orders- East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other groups
    - Woman, garbage, and dog, 1977 Sep. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Her foot was amputated after getting ganguerene [sic] from rat bite. Woman's grandson by window overlooking East 6th St., 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Hanging out"- local residents East 6th St. NYC, 1978 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Archive Material
  Series II. Archive material includes material from Stummer's archive of the East 6th Street photography project. This includes contact sheets, slides, audiotapes, a 9 minute reel-to-reel tape, "Children of East 6th Street" (which seems to be of still images), and a handmade artist's book of photographs and reminiscences of the project. This material spans the period from 1976 to 1984.
  One hundred and sixty printed contact sheets document the entirety of the images taken by Stummer on East 6th Street. Stummer's notes, as well as dates, are recorded on most of these. One hundred and sixty one slides, both black and white and Ektachrome, represent a selection of the images. Few are dated or labeled. The twelve audiotapes include several that Stummer recorded of ambient noise on the block while she was taking photographs. It also includes a tape of her narration to a slide show of photos of East 6th Street. Several tapes are oral histories and interviews between Stummer and East 6th Street residents.
  - Contact Sheets, 1977-1984 (Box 2)
  - Slides, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "East Sixth Street," artist's book, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reel to Reel Tape, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Audiotapes, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)